Guide to the Burton Turkus Collection BCMS.0016
Brooklyn Collection
Burton Turkus Collection
1921-1962
1938-1952
Brooklyn Collection
Turkus, Burton B.
BCMS.0016
1.75 Linear Feet in 4 document boxes
Materials documenting the career of Burton Turkus, who served as Chief of the Homicide Division for the District Attorney of Kings County and as the Assistant District Attorney, where he participated in the prosecution of the Murder, Inc. crime syndicate. Later in life he worked as an author and television personality.
Biographical Note
Burton Turkus was born in Brooklyn in 1902 to an immigrant watchmaker and a seamstress. After working the night shift as a telegraph operator at Western Union to pay for his courses, Turkus got his law degree through New York University and was admitted to the bar in 1925.
In 1940, Turkus was appointed Chief of the Homicide Division in the District Attorney of Kings County's office. It was at this time when Turkus took part in one the D.A. office's most famous cases, the "Murder, Inc." prosecution. He personally prosecuted many of the crime syndicate's leading members and obtained nine first-degree murder convictions, making him one of the nation's authorities on organized crime and racketeering. Through his success, Turkus became something of a local celebrity in Brooklyn and beyond, regularly appearing in newspapers and magazines, publishing books, articles, and hosting his own television show entitled Mr. Arsenic in 1952.
In 1942, Turkus ran for the position of County Judge without success, but played major roles in the campaigns of Thomas Dewey for Governor of New York in 1945 and President in 1948, serving as Chairman of the Citizens Non-Partisans Committee. Turkus was promoted to Chief Assistant District Attorney in 1945.Turkus also served as a member of the New York State Board of Mediation from 1947-1957, where he arbitrated and mediated in nearly a thousand labor management controversies for a diverse range of industries. Turkus led the way in implementing "instant arbitration," which allowed settlements to be made on labor disputes without a formal hearing.
Using his experience and expertise, Turkus participated in numerous projects to educate and entertain the country on the subjects of Murder Inc. and criminal prosecution, among other related topics. A film based on the Murder Inc. trials starring Humphrey Bogart entitled The Enforcer, on which Turkus served as a consultant was released in 1951. That same year, Turkus's book Murder Inc – The Story of the Syndicate was published and became a non-fiction bestseller. The book was the basis for the second feature film based on the trials, simply entitled Murder Inc. In the following years after publishing his memoir Turkus wrote for numerous publications including Readers Digest, Look Magazine, and New York Journal American. In 1953 Turkus headed the Advanced School for Detectives of the State of New Jersey, the first school of its kind to instruct law enforcement officers on the latest techniques in the apprehension of criminals and their prosecution, where he served as Director In Charge.
Turkus continued working on cases through the 1970s and died on November 22nd, 1982, leaving behind a wife and son.
Scope and Contents
The Burton Turkus Collection spans from 1921 to 1962, although the bulk of it is concentrated in the late 1930s to the early 1950s. The collection contains a variety of materials from the highlights of Turkus's career as District Attorney and prosecutor, as well as records and ephemera from his assistance to the electoral campaigns of Thomas Dewey and Turkus's own judicial campaign in 1942.
The files include trial preparation materials, photographs of crime scenes and suspect mug shots, charts and records summarizing the criminal careers of numerous defendants and summaries of trial testimony. Files from the various electoral campaigns include general correspondence, fundraising letters, photos, treasury documents, press releases and an assortment of other campaign materials.
Boxes 3 and 4 consist of newspaper and magazine clippings about the trials and other matters written by or relating to Turkus, as well as flyers, programs, and advertisements promoting his speaking engagements in the years following the trial.
Access
Collection is located in the Brooklyn Collection at the Central Branch at Grand Army Plaza. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Provenance
This collection was donated by Ann Turkus in 2000.
Related Archival Materials note
Articles from the Brooklyn Daily Eagle
Cipollini, Christian. Murder Inc.: mysteries of the mob's most deadly hit squad. Strategic Media Inc., 2015
Peterson, Virgil W. The mob: 200 years of organized crime in New York. Green Hill Publishers, 1983
Turks, Burton. Murder, inc. Manor Books, 1951
Other portions of Turkus' papers were donated to the Kheel Center at Cornell University and the Lloyd Sealy Library Special Collections at John Jay College of Criminal Justice.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in eight series:
Series I: Biographical Information contains three documents in one folder with no additional arrangement.
Series II: Murder, Inc. is arranged by type of document. Photographs in this series are presumed to be in original order.
Series III: Campaigns is arranged in two sub-series, both arranged by type of document.
Series IV: Photographs contains both loose photos and an album. Loose photos are not arranged, the album is presumed to be in original order.
Series V: George Beldock v. William O'Dwyer is not arranged.
Series VI: Clippings is arranged by type of publication. Articles from Look Magazine are held in a separate folder.
Series VII: Public Appearances is not arranged.
Series VIII: Correspondence and Court/Political Documents is arranged by type of document.
Brownsville (New York, N.Y.); Crime syndicates; Criminal records--New York (State); District attorneys; Election campaigns; Gangs--New York (State)--New York--History; Jewish criminals--New York (State)--New York; Murder Investigation; New York (State). Department of Law; Anastasia, Albert, 1902-1957; Buchalter, Louis, 1897-1944; Dewey, Thomas E, 1902-1971; Reles, Abe, 1906-1941; Strauss, Harry, 1909-1941
- Series I: Biographical Information
  - Biographical Information, 1908, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Murder, Inc.
  - Suspects and Criminal Records, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Trial Materials (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - State of NY v. Louis Buchalter, et al, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Amalgamated Clothing Workers Union Racketeering, 1931-1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Suspect Mugshots (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, Mugshots, Crime Scenes (Box 1, Binder 1)
- Series III: Campaigns
  - Sub-Series I: Burton Turkus Judicial Campaign
    - Clippings, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Subseries II: Thomas E. Dewey Presidential Campaign
    - Clippings and Promotional Materials, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Press Releases, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Citizens Non-Partisan Committee Treasury, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Photographs
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series V: George Beldock v. William O'Dwyer
  - Court Document, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Beldock Radio Addresses, 1931, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series VI: Clippings
  - Clippings, 1940-1953 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Clippings, Various Magazines, 1946-1958 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, Look Magazine, 1940, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters, 1933-1957 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series VII: Public Appearances
  - Flyers, Programs, Correspondence, 1942-1952 (Box 4, Folder 4-6)
- Series VIII: Correspondence and Court/Political Documents
  - Correspondence, 1925, 1948, 1959, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Court/Political Documents, circa 1948-1951 (Box 4, Folder 8)